Continuing our adventure through hyperparameters for training.
하이퍼파라미터에서 훈련을 계속하죠
The next one is pretty crucial and it is called learning Rate.
다음 단계는 아주 중요한 학습률이에요
And again, many data scientists amongst you will know this one only too well.
여러분 중 데이터 과학자들이 이걸 너무 잘 알 거예요
So for very, very quickly, for those that are less familiar with this, again the purpose of training
아주 잠깐, 이것에 덜 익숙한 분들을 위해 설명하자면 훈련의 목적은 여러분의 모델을
is that you take your model, you take a training data point.
트레이닝 데이터 포인트를 취하는 거죠
You do what they call a forward pass, which is an inference where you go through the model and say,
전진 패스라는 걸 하는데요 모델을 살펴보고 다음
predict the next token that should come, and it gives a prediction the the, the predicted next token.
토큰이 올지 예측하는 겁니다 예측된 다음 토큰을 주는 거죠
Or in fact, it gives a probabilities of all of the possible next tokens.
아니면 가능한 모든 다음 패의 확률을 주죠
And you use that and you have the actual next token that it should have actually been.
그걸 사용하면 실제 있어야 할 다음 토큰이 생기죠
And you can take these two, the prediction and the actual to come up with a loss.
이 두 가지를 예견하고 실제 손실을 계산해 보세요
How poorly did it do at predicting the actual and what you can then do is take that loss and you can
실제 비트를 예측하는 데 얼마나 형편없었는지를요 그런 다음 할 수 있는 건 손실을 받아들이고
do what they call back propagation when you go back through the model and figure out how sensitive,
그것의 역전파를 할 수 있습니다 모델로 돌아가서 각 비트를 얼마나 민감하게 조정해야
how much would I have to tweak each weight up or down in order to do a little bit better next time?
하는지 알아내는 거죠 다음에 좀 더 잘하기 위해 각 비트를 얼마나 조정할까요?
Uh, and then you have to take a step in the direction.
그 방향으로 한 걸음씩 나아가야 해요
You have to shift your weights, a step in the direction to do better next time.
역기를 옮겨야 해요 다음번엔 더 잘하도록 한 걸음씩 나아가는 거죠
And that step, that amount that you shift your weights in a good direction so that it will do a little
비트를 좋은 방향으로 많이 옮겨야 다음번에 더
bit better next time.
잘 걸리죠
When faced with exactly that training data point, uh, is called the learning rate.
훈련 데이터 포인트를 마주했을 때 학습률이라고 하죠
And it's typically it's it's either 0.0001 or 0.00001.
일반적으로 0 정도 돼요 0001이나 0요 00001년요
Uh, you will see some examples when we go through it.
살펴보면 몇 가지 예가 보일 거예요
And there's also an ability to do have what's called a learning rate scheduler, which is when you start
또 학습률 스케줄러라는 기능도 있습니다 여러
the learning rate at one number and during the course of your run over the period of several epochs,
개혁을 거치면서 학습률을 한 숫자로 시작해서 점점
you gradually lower it and lower it and lower it, because as your model gets more trained, you want
낮추는 거죠 모델이 훈련될수록 학습률이
your learning rate, the amount of step that you take to get shorter and shorter and shorter until you're
점점 낮아져서 네트워크에 아주 작은 변화만
only making tiny Any adjustments to your network.
줄어드는 거예요
Because you're pretty confident that you're in the right vicinity.
거의 맞혔다고 확신하고 있잖아요
So that is learning rates.
이게 학습률이에요
Again, it will be old hat to many people who have a data science background.
데이터 과학을 전공한 많은 사람들에겐 익숙한 일이겠죠
It might be new to others.
다른 사람에겐 생소할 수 있죠
Gradient accumulation is a way.
그러데이션 축적도 방법이에요
It's it's a technique that allows you to improve speed of going through training where you say, okay,
훈련 속도를 높이는 기술이에요 이렇게 말할 수 있죠 우리가
so what we're going to do is we're going to we normally do a forward pass.
뭘 할 거냐면 보통은 앞으로 패스해요
We get the, the, the, the, the loss as I just described it.
방금 말한 것처럼 get 손실이 발생하죠
We then work out the gradients going backwards and then we take a step in the right direction.
그리고 뒤로 가는 그러데이션을 계산해서 올바른 방향으로 한 걸음씩 나아가는 거죠
And then we repeat gradient accumulation says well perhaps what we can do is we can do a forward pass
그러한 그러데이션 누적 현상을 반복해 보면 이렇게 말할 수 있죠 앞으로 패스해서
and get the gradients and don't take a step, just do a second forward pass and get the gradients and
얻으면 어떨까? 한 걸음씩 가지 않고 두 번째 패스해서 얻으면 어떨까?
add up those gradients and do that a few more times.
그 과정을 몇 번 더 반복하는 거죠
Just keep accumulating these gradients and then take a step and then optimize the network.
이런 그러데이션을 계속 축적하고 한 단계씩 나아가 네트워크를 최적화하세요
And that just means that you do these steps less frequently, which means it can run a bit faster.
이 단계를 비정상적으로 수행하면 비트 코드가 더 빨라지죠
Um, in some ways it's a bit similar to batch size.
비트 크기와 비슷할 거예요
It has some some there's some sort of a conceptual similarities there, because you're sort of grouping
개념적 유사점이 있어요 왜냐하면 함께 그룹을 이루고
things together and just taking one slightly bigger step.
약간 더 큰 단계를 밟으니까요
Um, in the hyperparameters that I've set up, I'm not using gradient accumulation.
제가 설정한 hyperpaameter에는 그러데이션 축적을 사용하지 않아요
I've got that set to one.
1로 설정했어요
But I did try it in the past, and I see how it speeds things up.
하지만 전에 해봤는데 속도가 빨라지는 걸 봤어요
And so you might well be interested in experimenting with that and see what it does.
그러니 이 방법으로 실험해 보고 어떻게 되는지 보세요
So that is gradient accumulation.
이게 그러데이션 축적이에요
And then last but not least the optimizer.
마지막은 최적화 장치예요
The optimizer is the formula that's used when it's time, when you've got the gradients you've got your
최적화 프로그램은 적절한 때에 사용하는 공식이에요 그러데이션이 되면 학습률이
learning rate.
올라가죠
And it's time to now make an update to your neural network to shift everything a little bit in a good
이제 신경망을 업데이트할 시간이에요 모든 걸 좋은 방향으로 약간씩 바꾸면
direction, so that next time it's that little bit more likely to predict the right next token.
다음에는 올바른 토큰을 예측할 가능성이 커지죠 비트
And the process for doing that is called the optimizer.
그 과정을 최적화 장치라고 하죠
And there are a bunch of well-known formulae for how you could do that, each with pros and cons, you'll
그 방법에 관한 잘 알려진 공식이 아주 많은데 각각 장단점이 있죠 그중 하나를
see we pick one in particular.
선택할게요
That's one that is a little bit more expensive in terms of the performance.
비트는 성능 면에서 조금 더 비싸죠
It's a it's a bit harder work, but it leads to good outcomes.
비트 박스는 좀 힘들지만 좋은 결과를 낳아요
So it's the one that I would recommend starting with.
이 제품부터 시작하시길 추천해요
And then if you do end up having any kind of memory problems, there are alternatives that are, um,
그리고 메모리 문제가 발생하면 메모리 소모량을 줄여주는
that consume less memory.
대안이 있어요
But that that process is called optimization.
하지만 그 과정을 최적화라고 하죠
And the algorithm that you pick to do it is called the optimizer.
그 작업을 위해 선택한 알고리즘을 최적화 장치라고 해요
And it's another hyperparameter, and that you can try different ones and see how they do.
또 다른 hyperperameter죠 다양한 걸 시도해보고 어떤지 보세요
So I realize it's an awful lot of talking.
말이 너무 많다는 걸 깨달았어요
And I've also used the the conversation about hyperparameters to explain a bit about the training process.
hyperperameter에 대한 대화도 비트로 사용했어요 훈련 프로세스에 대해 설명하려고요
Uh, but hopefully this was good foundational background that's prepared you for what is just about
지금까지 배운 배경이 도움이 됐길 바랍니다 앞으로 일어날
to happen now, which is we're going back to Google Colab, where we are going to set up and kick off
일에 대비해서요 구글 Colab으로 돌아가 SFT 트레이너를
our SFT trainer to fine tune our own, uh, specialized LM.
시작할 겁니다 우리만의 LM을 세밀하게 조정하기 위해서요